Finding Aid for Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan), 1947-
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gilbert and Sullivan Society (University of Michigan), publications 1947-ongoing
University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.
2 linear ft.
Publications of University of Michigan organization which produces Gilbert and Sullivan operettas, including flyers, newsletters and a history of the organization.
97133 Bimu F71 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Publications have been received from Harry Benford (donor # 3123 ) and are received periodically from the unit (donor # 8613 ).
The publications are open for research.
The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (UMGASS) traces its origins to the fall of 1946, when University of Michigan freshman Gloria Katlan (later Bennish) called a campus-wide meeting for those interested in the production of a Gilbert and Sullivan operetta. Organizational concerns occupied the Society's attention for the first year, and it was not until the fall of 1947 that members staged a first performance of the Mikado. Since that date, the Society has produced at least two operettas each year, going through the repertoire of thirteen Gilbert and Sullivan operettas every six or seven years.
UMGASS is an officially recognized University of Michigan student organization, but membership is not limited to students. Any interested person may participate in UMGASS productions or hold office in the Society. Under conditions set by its constitution, UMGASS business is managed by a small governing board elected annually by active participants in the productions. The board selects each year's directors and selects and produces the shows. Since 1969, UMGASS has been encouraged and supported by a group called the Friends of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (FUMGASS). Chief among FUMGASS's activities has been the production of a journal of Gilbert and Sullivan news and events, both on the University of Michigan campus and worldwide. The journal's acronym, GASBAG, stands for Gilbert and Sullivan Boys and Girls.
Professor Harry Benford, of the Department of Naval Architecture, and his wife have served as UMGASS faculty advisors since 1956. They were particularly active during the years 1962-1982 and were instrumental in the formation of FUMGASS. Professor Benford served as GASBAG editor from 1969 through 1982, when he and his wife retired from the University.
The Publications series (2 linear feet) includes flyers, programs, newsletters, and a history of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society as well as the newsletter of the Friends of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society. The publications are divided into two series: Unit Publications and Sub-Unit Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society.; University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society. Friends.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; University of Michigan. Gilbert and Sullivan Society. Friends.; Pudding full of plums.
Genre/Form:
Histories.; Newsletters.; Programs.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series includes flyers announcing future productions, ticket prices, and casts. There is also a history entitled A Pudding Full of Plums: The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society's First Fifty Years by long-time advisor Harry Benford. It was published in 1997 to commemorate the fiftieth anniversary of the society. This series also includes programs, dating from 1958 to the present, of the various operettas produced in Ann Arbor and other locations in the state by the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society.
  - Brochures, 1972-2005 and undated (Box 1)
  - Flyers, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Histories
    - A Pudding Full of Plums: The University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society's First Fifty Years by Harry Benford, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1947-2011 and undated, 47 folders (Box 1)
  - UMGASS 50th Anniversary Memory Book, 1997 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications subseries includes the newsletter The Gasbag published by the Friends of the University of Michigan Gilbert and Sullivan Society (FUMGASS). The Bentley Historical Library has a complete run of this publication from 1969 to the present.
  - Friends of the Gilbert and Sullivan Society
    - Newsletters
      - The Gasbag
        - Vol. 1-10, 1969-1979, 10 folders (Box 1)
        - Vol. 11-39, 1979-2011, 28 folders (Box 2)